

Website: <a href="https://http

Austin, TX

(347) 831-6041 hanafrla@utexas.edu

**Profile** 

## **PhD Student at University of Texas at Austin**

Interested in researching social aspects of modern technology to facilitate a more inclusive future, specifically in the context of open source software communities and diverse participation.

Education

# **University of Texas at Austin**; Austin, TX

08/2021 - Present

Pursuing a doctoral degree in Information Studies at the Information School

- Faculty Advisor: Professor James Howison

## Carnegie Mellon University; Pittsburgh, PA

08/2016 - 05/2020

B.Sc. Electrical and Computer Engineering

- Minor in Human-Computer Interaction, advised by Professor Laura Dabbish

**Publications** 

- Li, Renee, Pavitthra Pandurangan, **Hana Frluckaj**, and Laura Dabbish. "Code of Conduct Conversations in Open Source Software Projects on Github." *Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction* 5, no. CSCW1 (2021): 1-31.
- Contribution: Helped analyze and categorize sample of conversations to develop typology on code of conduct conversations

Hana Frluckaj, Laura Dabbish, David Gray Widder, James D. Herbsleb "Gender and Participation in Open Source Software Development" In: *Conference on Computer-supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing* (CSCW 2022)

- Contribution: Interviewed half of participants, transcribed and coded all transcripts, employed grounded theory to compare men and women's career trajectories.

Tamar Wilner, Krishna Akhil Kumar Adavi, Sreehana Mandava, Ayesha Bhimdiwala, **Hana Frluckaj**, Jennifer Turns, and Ahmer Arif Wilner, "From Concept to Community: Unpacking the Work of Designing Educational and Activist Toolkits." In *Proceedings of the CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems* (pp. 1-15). CHI (2024)

- Contribution: Helped to conduct interviews and direct methodological approach, and relate toolkit making practices to maintenance in OSS work.

**Hana Frluckaj**, Huilian Qiu, Laura Dabbish, Bogdan Vasilescu, "From the Inside Out: Organizational Impact on Open-Source Communities and Women's Representation." In *Proceedings of the 2024 IEEE/ACM 17th International Conference on Cooperative and Human Aspects of Software Engineering* (pp. 36-50). (ICSE-CHASE 2024)

- Contribution: Interviewed all the participants and directed grounded theory approach.

In Press

**Hana Frluckaj**, James Howison, Qiwei Li, Laura Dabbish, "Codes of Conduct in Open Source," Textbook on Equity, Diversity, and Inclusion in Software Engineering (2024)

**Hana Frluckaj**, James Howison, Laura Dabbish, Nikki Stevens "Paradoxes of Openness and Trans Experiences in Open Source Software" CSCW (2024)

**Research Experience** 

#### PhD Student

05/2020 - Present

- Studying the experiences of under-represented and marginalized contributors in OSS
- Studying the organizational influence on OSS project diversity and newcomer retention
- Analyzing GitHub conversations regarding codes of conduct and governance
- Designing a panel study to understand OSS work-life balance in order to understand and encourage diverse participation

**Graduate Research Intern, Los Alamos National Lab**; Los Alamos, NM 05/2023 - 12/2023 Directed LANL team on grounded theory (GT) approach to analyze the phenomenon of muliteam collaboration, including open source collaboration, of the Exascale Computing Project. Provided training on GT, helped conduct interviews, participated in multiple rounds of coding and comparison discussions, and developed a codebook.

## **Graduate Research Assistant, UT iSchool;** Austin, TX

01/2023 - 05/2023

Participated in a research project headed by Dr. Ahmer Arif on the process of building and maintaining toolkits, with emphasis on combatting misinformation and aiding under resourced communities. Helped conduct interviews, trained and mentored undergraduate RAs, offered insights in team research discussions, connected emerging results to other fields of literature, and built shareable, informative materials for the broader research team.

#### Research Assistant, Human-Computer Interaction Institute, CMU 09/2019 - 05/2020

- Empirical qualitative study analyzing diversity and inclusion in open source.
- Screened 4000+ users, recruited and interviewed 21 participants, created a coding scheme following grounded theory, resulting in my first first-authored paper.

# Research Assistant, Institute for Software Research, CMU

09/2018 - 05/2019

Project validated a new fault-injection framework by retrofitting existing open source applications, developing models of expected application results, and creating a general server in Erlang within Partisan protocol to accomplish hierarchical clustering.

## Research Assistant, Electrical and Computer Engineering, CMU

05/2018 - 08/2018

Project involved building and programming a wireless system for neural recording, capable of streaming digitized data to a remote machine for analysis. Project required system design, PCB sketching and milling, and embedded systems application.

#### **Working Experience**

**Managing Editorial Fellow, Information & Culture Journal;** Austin, TX 09/2023 - Present Currently managing the Information & Culture Journal. Involves fielding and assessing submitted manuscripts, finding reviewers, guiding both authors and reviewers through the review process, copyediting, and coordinating between authors, reviewers, the editorial team, and UT Press.

## IT Assistant, Institute for Software Research; Pittsburgh, PA

09/2016 - 05/2020

Performed diagnostics and initial troubleshooting tasks, investigated hardware and software issues, and assisted 120+ students, staff, and faculty with technological needs.

## Technology Analyst, Deutsche Bank; New York, NY

06/2019 - 08/2019

Built a simulator for messages sent between international credit/debit tracking systems in Java using Spring environment. In parallel, built and presented a sentiment analysis application focusing on public traded companies, their stocks, and media bias in Python using ML and NLP. Advocated for increased diversity in presentations and discussions.

### Engineering Aide, Consolidated Edison, Inc.; New York, NY

07/2015 - 08/2017

- 05/2017 08/2017: Built test scripts and aided IT programmers in identifying algorithmic fallacies in OBIEE Performance Manager within Public Engineering.
- 09/2015 07/2016: Reviewed data filing for over 4000 work requests, organized data lists of employee review calls, and maintained documentation of ConEd facilities.
- 07/2015 09/2015: Reviewed conflicts of the energy grid, worked with external agencies, and compiled estimate cost data in Excel.

Skills

**Programming Languages:** Python, C/C++, Processing, Verilog, Java, Erlang, Go, and Matlab **Technical:** Unix/Linux, Computer Security, Computer Systems, Sentiment Analysis, Digital Signal Processing, Test-Driven Development, User Experience Design, Human-Robot Interaction, and Computer Graphics

**Research:** GitHub repository mining, qualitative analysis, Grounded Theory, recruitment, interviewing, affinity diagrams, and literature reviews

Spoken Languages: English (Native), Serbo-Croatian (Native), French (Working)

Service

UT-Austin iSchool Research Community Committee 08/2023 - Present
UT-Austin iSchool Undergraduate Studies Committee 08/2022 - 08/2023
UT-Austin iSchool Diversity and Inclusion Committee 08/2021 - 08/2022

Hawaii International Conference on Systems Sciences (HICSS) 2022 - Reviewer

SIGBOVIK 2021 - Moderation Chair

Women in Cybersecurity (WiCyS) 2019 - Student Volunteer

**Students Mentored** 

Cindy Hyunh, student at UT-Austin 01/2024 - 05/2024

Magali Astride Ngouabou Noubissi, graduated Pomona University 06/2020 - 05/2023

	Raaka Mukhopadhyay, student at Carnegie Mellon University.	01/2021 - 05/2021
Organizations	iPride and DEI Lab; UT-Austin	01/2022 - Present
	Critical Data Studies Group; UT-Austin	09/2023 - Present
	International Student Union; CMU	02/2017 - 05/2020
	Held the positions of President, Treasurer, and Secretary.	
	Women in ECE; CMU	09/2016 - 05/2020
	Society of Women Engineers; CMU	09/2016 - 05/2020
	Girls Who Code; Brooklyn Technical High School	09/2015 - 08/2016
	Held the position of Mentor.	
Travel Awards		Amount Awarded:
	International Conference of Software Engineering (ICSE) 2024	\$1488
	Lisbon, Portugal 2024	
	Diversity in Scientific Computing (DISC) UnConference 2023	\$1,945
	Amsterdam, NL 2023	
	International Conference of Software Engineering (ICSE) 2022  Pittsburgh, PA, USA 2022	\$1200
	Vive la Différence Workshop 2022 - Research Software Engineers	€1550
	Lorentz Center, Leiden, NL 2022	
References	Associate Professor James Howison: howison@ischool.utexas.edu	
	Associate Professor Laura Dabbish: dabbish@cmu.edu	